בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף Daf is כ Kaf and we
pick up with the משנה Mishna on the bottom of י"ט עמוד
ב' Yud Tes Amud Beis and God willing we will end the
first פרק Perek and begin the second פרק Perek today. So let's
take a look. After a whole משנה Mishna of debates of בית
שמאי Beis Shammai and בית הלל Beis Hillel about things that you
can begin from before שבת Shabbos and continue into שבת Shabbos or
according to בית שמאי Beis Shammai that you cannot, including whether it's
a process going on its own or relates to a non-Jew if
the non-Jew is doing it for you or even if the non-Jew
is doing it on his own. And then we had one case
where they all agreed upon which was that you are allowed to
have the wine press and olive press, the beam sort of continuing
to push down the olives or the wine to take out the
wine. This משנה Mishna switches to a case that they all agree
about to be strict that presumably even בית הלל Beis Hillel says
you're not allowed to do. Let's take a look. אין צולין בשר
בצל וביצה אלא כדי שיצולו מבעוד יום. Ein tsolin basar batsal uveitsa
ela kedei sheyitsolu mibe'od yom.
You do not roast ערב שבת Erev Shabbos meat or an onion
or eggs, an egg, unless it has the ability to roast from
the day before. So you do not have this continuing to roast
on שבת. Shabbos. Now, אין, Ein, now this is, well let's finish,
let's read the whole משנה. Mishna. אין נותנין פת לתנור עם חשיכה,
Ein notnin pat letanur im chashecha, you cannot put bread into the
oven as it gets dark, ולא חררה על גבי גחלים, velo charara
al gabei gechalim, or not a wafer, a biscuit, on top of
coals, that's how they would make a biscuit, אלא כדי שיקרמו פניה
מבעוד
יום, ela kedei sheyekremu paneiha mibe'od yom, unless you have time that
the crust hardened from the day before, that it forms a crust,
and then it's considered enough cooked that it's okay. רבי אליעזר אומר
כדי שיקרם התחתון שלה. Rabbi Eliezer omer kedei sheyekrem hatachton shela. It
doesn't have to be the crust on all sides or whatever, just
the crust on the bottom side. We'll see in the גמרא Gemara
how to understand רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer. משלשלין את הפסח בתנור עם
חשיכה. Meshalshelin et hapesach betanur im chashecha.
Now while you're not allowed to roast various things, this of course
would be a classic thing you would roast would be the קרבן
פסח, Korban Pesach, and nevertheless you are allowed to lower the פסח.
Pesach. משלשל Meshalshel means like to lower it into an oven because
even when they would roast things, they would have a fire going
in an oven and they'd have the spit over the fire and
it would but in order to sort of concentrate the heat, it
wouldn't be an open fire barbecue, it would be within the oven.
So one minute you would lower the פסח Pesach into the oven
עם חשיכה im chashecha as it would darken. Now this is not
a normal ערב פסח Erev Pesach because you're allowed to cook on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. This is an ערב Erev where פסח Pesach
is שבת. Shabbos. So פסח Pesach is שבת, Shabbos, right, so you
can't be cooking on שבת Shabbos itself but you can lower it
into the oven as it gets dark right before it gets dark.
Okay and that actually is a line quoted from a משנה Mishna
in פסחים Pesachim about how they would bring the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach when it would be on שבת. Shabbos. That is allowed although
other things are not. A special exception to a קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, we'll see why. ומאחיזין את האור במדורת בית המוקד. Umaachizin et
haur bemidurat Beit HaMoked. Now that we're talking all of these things,
you notice how they have a common denominator which is what? All
these issues are talking about what?
What are they talking about? They all talking about cooking and fire.
Right. So that's the common denominator here and that's the things that
are problematic, okay, as opposed to other processes that בית הלל Beis
Hillel allowed you to begin. These are all fire-related. Similarly you can
begin a fire in the מדורת בית המוקד, Midurat Beit HaMoked, those
who were with us at the end of קדשים Kodshim remember about
the בית המוקד Beit HaMoked which was the place where the כהנים
Kohanim in the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash would go to warm themselves
up. They would have to be barefoot on the stone floor of
the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash so there would be a special place
there that they would have a nice burning fire that they could
go and warm themselves up, a special room. So you are allowed
to light that fire in the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash. Now what
does that mean? Does it mean on שבת? Shabbos? Does it mean
ערב שבת? Erev Shabbos? So presumably it means on ערב שבת Erev
Shabbos and it means that you can as long as you begin
the fire ערב שבת Erev Shabbos right before it gets dark you
don't have to wait for the fire to really catch on. And
that's in contrast to the next line. Top of כ עמוד א'.
Kaf Amud Aleph. ובגבולין כדי שתאחוז האור ברובה. Uvagvulin kedei sheteechoz haur
berubah.
If you want to start a fire in your house outside the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash on ערב שבת, Erev Shabbos, it is only
when it's only okay if the fire has caught onto most of
the wood pile. Okay because then you're not going to fiddle with
the fire. Okay this really brings us to a time when keeping
a fire was not a trivial thing. Now we just turn on
the gas or we turn on the electricity in one second. Right.
You have to build a fire. If anybody went camping, right, it
takes a lot of effort to get it started to make sure
it keeps on going. Okay so we're afraid that you're going to
come to fiddle with it on שבת. Shabbos. So outside of the
בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash we insist that it's mostly it has taken
seized most of the wood pile. רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer,
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says, בפחמים כל שהוא. bepechamim kol shehu. That's
if it's normal wood. But if you're dealing with charcoal then even
if it just began to burn part of the charcoal you're okay
ערב שבת Erev Shabbos because charcoal as we know burns easily and
you don't have to worry once it starts burning. No discussion about
lighter fluid. Okay anyway so now as we said the common... denominator
here is fire, and it's worth pointing out that the משנה Mishna
began, well not the משנה, Mishna, when we got to the גזירות
Gezeirot about ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, one of the first גזירות Gezeirot
of ערב שבת Erev Shabbat in this, in this פרק Perek was
about reading by firelight. So there seems to have been a very
prevalent concern, strong concern, that you're about fiddling with a fire. And
again, usually not the concern is that you know it's שבת Shabbat
and you willfully violate. Sometimes we have that concern that חז״ל Chazal
say people are so anxious about their money, so it's dealt with
like, you know, if you find yourself trapped outside of the city
with your wallet on you. But mostly these concerns are about if
somebody's going to willfully violate, they'll go against the דרבנן derabbanan as
well, but it's a concern that you'll get preoccupied and you'll forget
that it's שבת. Shabbat. And particularly about a fire, you know, you're
so you're going to twiddle with it, you're going to forget it's
שבת, Shabbat, and that's why we have all of these concerns. So
even בית הלל, Beit Hillel, that normally says you can start a
process before שבת, Shabbat, when it comes to starting a fire, when
it comes to cooking things on a fire, there they say we've
got to make sure the fire is burning well, we've got to
make sure the thing is getting on the process of being cooked.
It's basically not maybe fully cooked, we'll see in the גמרא, Gemara,
but it's well along the way because when those aren't true, you
know, you'll be anxious about it and you'll forget and you'll come
to fiddle with the fire, that presumably is the concern. I should
say though, with all that being said, and I did mention to
you that the תוספתא Tosefta makes it clear that בית שמאי Beit
Shammai and בית הלל Beit Hillel had accepted two rulings. One is
that you can have the beam in the wine vat and the
olive vat, that that's okay from ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, and the
fire and the things that are roasted ערב שבת Erev Shabbat is
a problem. And the question was that the debate of הלל Hillel
and שמאי Shammai is what's the general rule? General rule can you
start things ערב שבת Erev Shabbat or can you not? That being
said, there is one מדרש הלכה, Midrash Halacha, the מכילתא, Mechilta, that
says that this משנה Mishna אין צולין בשר בצל ein tzolim basar
batzel is position of בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. It's בית שמאי Beit
Shammai being consistent with his position of starting things, and that בית
הלל Beit Hillel would actually disagree with that. That's not how רבי
Rebbi understood it, it's not how the גמרא Gemara understands it, it's
understood that this is universally accepted for the reason I said that
when dealing with fire, and we see that from the beginning, from
the issues of reading by firelight, there's a heightened concern that you
will come to forget and to fiddle with it. Okay, now so
let's take a look now at the גמרא. Gemara. וכמה? Vechama? So
it says it has things that's roasting has to be roasted from
the day before. How well roasted does it have to be that
you're okay?
So אמר רבי אלעזר אמר רב, Amar Rabbi Elazar Amar Rav, כדי
שיצולו מבעוד יום כמאכל בן דרוסאי. kedei she-yitzolu miba'od yom kema'achal Ben
Drusai. So this thing of מאכל בן דרוסאי Ma'achal Ben Drusai is
an idea that comes up in the גמרא Gemara a lot, the
eating of בן דרוסאי. Ben Drusai. This person בן דרוסאי Ben Drusai
would like his meat very like you know rare, and
there's a רש״י Rashi says he was like a bandit so he
couldn't waste the time to actually cook his meat well done. Anyway,
there's a debate whether that means a third cooked, whether it means
a half cooked. I also have to admit I never really understood
whether a third or a half meant you take the total amount
of time it takes to cook it and you divide like you
divide by three or you divide by half. So if it normally
takes like an hour to fully cook we're talking about a half
hour, or does it mean no, like you know you can look
at something, you know rare, medium rare, well done, maybe this just
means like rare, which is not necessarily the same as the a
half of the amount of time or third of the amount of
time. But this is a very important principle that we will see
when we get to keeping stuff on the fire before שבת Shabbat
and the general issue about having a בלעך blech and so on,
which will be the focus of the third פרק. Perek. That there's
a stage where you're allowed to put it on the fire if
it's cooked well enough, and according to some, that is when it
is מאכל בן דרוסאי, Ma'achal Ben Drusai, which means either a third
or a half cooked. That's how the אשכנזים Ashkenazim פסקן. pasken. Just
to jump a little ahead, the ספרדים Sephardim פסקן pasken that no,
if you don't want a בלעך blech ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, something
has to be fully cooked. It's not enough that it's מאכל בן
דרוסאי. Ma'achal Ben Drusai. But interestingly, that debate does not appear by
the case of roasting. This משנה Mishna of roasting is taught independently
of the third פרק, Perek, which is all devoted to keeping your
food on the fire ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. So that's interesting why
it's separated off. But there are some different rules. So for example,
here because roasting happens much more quickly than cooking, everybody agrees that
once it's a third cooked, you're okay. When it becomes by more
gradual cooking, some say it has to be fully cooked if you
want to leave it on the fire without a בלעך. blech. There's
one other difference I should just mention, which wasn't so black and
white in the גמרא, Gemara, but remember we had a קולא kula
about putting stuff on the fire right before שבת. Shabbat. Do you
remember what was the קולא kula about when you can put stuff
on the fire right before
שבת? Shabbat? If it's not cooked at all, it's raw, because then
you forget about it till the next morning. Well, the גמרא Gemara
was implicit and the ראשונים Rishonim were explicit, they say it doesn't
apply by roasting, right? Because roasting, it cooks very quickly, so so
it applies like if you have a טשולנט cholent and you know
it's not going to get ready till tomorrow and because you put
in some raw meat, so you don't need a בלעך blech because
you're going to forget about it till tomorrow. But by roasting, even
if it's raw it's a problem, because it's going to roast pretty
quickly and you're still focused on it. So there's one stringency about
roasting that even if it's raw it's a problem, because it's going
to roast pretty quickly and you're still focused on it. raw, you
don't have that leniency, but on the other hand there's a leniency
that once it's a third cooked or a half cooked, everybody says
it's okay, it does not need a בלעך blech because then it's
going to be finished so quickly, we're not concerned that you would
be fiddling with it once it's got to that stage. Okay, so
this is the idea of roasting and I'm just trying to put
in the context of the third פרק perek which we will see
later, which ignores this משנה mishnah and focuses on cooking, this משנה
mishnah deals with roasting. איתמר נמי itmar nami was taught as well,
אמר רב אסי אמר רבי יוחנן amar Rav Assi amar Rabbi Yochanan
כל שהוא כמאכל בן דרוסאי kol shehu kemachal ben drosai אין בו
משום בישולי נכרים. ein bo mishum bishulei nochrim. Now this is not
taught about our משנה, mishnah, but it's an analogy. Something, food is
cooked by non-Jews, if it's a type of food that usually goes
by two criteria, number one cannot be eaten raw and number two
is ראוי לעלות על שלחן מלכים raui la'alot al shulchan melachim is
fit for kings, so there was a prohibition about not having that
food that was cooked by non-Jews because a concern of too much
interaction and, you know, fraternizing and leading to intermarriage. And there are,
but there are exceptions, and one exception is besides the two I
mentioned, is that if it's already, the cooking began by a Jew,
you're okay. So what does it mean began by a Jew? So
it says once a Jew cooked it to the point that it's
מאכל בן דרוסאי machal ben drosai again, either a half or a
third cooked, then it is already considered cooked by a Jew, it's
considered cooked, and if a non-Jew finishes it you're okay. Now, we
actually אשכנזים Ashkenazim have adopted a leniency that even if the Jew
just turns on the fire, even you know, that that's okay, but
anyway that came after the גמרא, Gemara, in the גמרא Gemara what
you're, whatever, it's based on a little line in the גמרא. Gemara.
But anyway, here it says as long as you cooked it to
מאכל בן דרוסאי, machal ben drosai, so you see that is considered
to be cooked enough that it's edible. So therefore by analogy, if
that's true by בישולי עכו"ם, bishulei akum, it's also by our משנה,
mishnah, once the roasted meat is cooked to that degree, you're not
concerned that you will come to, it's considered cooked and it's okay,
and you don't have to be concerned that you'll come to fiddle
with the fire or whatnot. תניא tanya we taught in a ברייתא,
braita, חנניה אומר Chananya omer כל שהוא כמאכל בן דרוסאי kol shehu
kemachal ben drosai מותר להשהותו על גבי כירה mutar lehash'hoto al gabei
kirah thank you so much, ואף על פי שאינו גרופה וקטומה. v'af
al pi she'eino grufah u'ktumah. Now this is directly taken from the
third פרק. perek. Because here notice we have a different context, we
have כירה, kirah, כירה kirah is an oven, we're no longer talking
about a roasting or a תנור, tanur, we're talking about a כירה,
kirah, and we're talking about a cooking, we're not talking about roasting.
And the phrase of
אף על פי להשהותו af al pi lehash'hoto to leave it, שהייה
shehiyah is the phrase about, about the third פרק, perek, about leaving
things on the fire ערב שבת, erev Shabbat, and גרופה וקטומה grufah
u'ktumah is what we translate as a בלעך. blech. גרופה וקטומה grufah
u'ktumah is how could you leave things on the fire before שבת?
Shabbat? If you swept out the oven, you swept it out from
the burning, you know, coals, or you קטומה, ktumah, you put ashes
on the coals so they were basically on the way to extinguishing.
So we, our modern form of putting ashes on the coals is
putting a בלעך blech over the fire. Okay, but that is what
we will see in the third פרק, perek, that is basically the
idea, if you want stuff to cook on your stove ערב שבת,
erev Shabbat, you have to, if, you have to have it גרופה
וקטומה, grufah u'ktumah, which swept out or ashes put on, which for
us means a בלעך, blech, unless says חנניה, Chananya, it's מאכל בן
דרוסאי. machal ben drosai. If it gets to the stage of מאכל
בן דרוסאי, machal ben drosai, a third or half cooked, then you
can leave it on without a בלעך. blech. Okay, so what he
is, this is basically doing is connecting this discussion of roasting to
the entire third פרק perek which focuses on the issue of leaving
stuff on the stove ערב שבת. erev Shabbat. Okay, and here for
חנניה Chananya it's the same, but as I said, for others it's
not. Roasting we all say goes by a third cooked, whereas by
leaving something cooking on a pot on the stove ערב שבת, erev
Shabbat, according to some opinions only after it's fully cooked, anything less
than that you do need a בלעך. blech. Okay, so again, this
משנה mishnah is about roasting, it seems to be agreed by בית
שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל. Beit Hillel. Why? Presumably something relating
to fire, everybody agrees is a concern, interestingly taught out of the
context of the third פרק, perek, which is completely devoted to food
on the fire ערב שבת, erev Shabbat, but here the גמרא Gemara
connects the two, at least according to חנניה Chananya that says both
about third פרק perek issues and this issue, once it's a third
cooked you're okay. Okay, now the גמרא Gemara continues. I should just
say one final thing because we mentioned בישולי נכרים, bishulei nochrim, you
know, about the eighteen things of בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית
הלל, Beit Hillel, according to our גמרא Gemara basically like seventeen out
of them were all טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah or sixteen of them,
and like the last one or two had to do with interactions
with non-Jews, with like the bread, the wine, the oil, and so
on. According to one opinion in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi, רבי שמעון בר
יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, all eighteen of them were about interactions
with non-Jews, and lists eighteen different ways in which, you know, separations
of Jews and non-Jews. So some that were listed here, you know,
and many others. So I just thought that's interesting to think about
like, you know, both of those were very prevalent concerns in the
time of שמאי והלל Shammai v'Hillel and towards the end of the
בית שני Bayit Sheni period, one was טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah and
the other was the interactions with the non-Jews and especially with like
the. oppressive Roman government.
So it's quite fascinating that the בבלי Bavli emphasizes the טומאה וטהרה
tumah v'taharah and the ירושלמי Yerushalmi the non-Jews, one and at least
but it has a ברייתא baraita of רב שמעון בר יוחאי Reb
Shimon bar Yochai to that effect. It is true in general that
the בבלי Bavli has a much more positive attitude towards the non-Jewish
government. They were in a much more welcoming and hospitable non-Jewish country
than those that were living in ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. But it
is worth noting that according to one approach in the ירושלמי, Yerushalmi,
all of the eighteen things were like בישולי נכרים bishulei nochrim and
all these different ways they're separating Jews and non-Jews. Okay, so now
back to the גמרא. Gemara. אין נותנין את הפת. Ein notnin et
hapas. You cannot put bread in the oven similar to the roasting,
that's also something that gets done relatively quickly. You cannot do it
unless until unless there's ערב שבת erev Shabbat unless there's time for
the crust to form. So the גמרא Gemara says, and then what's-his-name,
רבי אליעזר Rebi Eliezer says the bottom crust. איבעיא להו. Ibayah lehu.
They raised the question. תחתון היכא דגבי תנור או דילמא תחתון היכא
דגבי האור? Tachton heicha degabei tanur o dilma tachton heicha degabei ha'ur?
When they say bottom, do you mean the bottom, the side facing
the wall of the oven? Or do you mean... this רש״י Rashi
we're assuming here that the בבלי Bavli assumes that you're making bread
sort of like the way you make like, you know, אש תנור
esh tanur pita, which you basically slap like, you know some bread...
yeah it has a picture there, right? You slap it on the
side of the wall of the oven. So the side of the
bread that's on the wall of the oven gets crusted last. The
side that is facing the fire gets crusted first. So when we
say he says the bottom one, is he being strict and saying
the face facing the wall? So he's being more strict. Or is
he being lenient and saying the face of the bread facing the
oven? תא שמע. Ta shma. רבי אליעזר אומר כדי שיקרמו פניה המדובקים
בתנור. Rebi Eliezer omer kedei sheyakrimu paneha hamidubakim batanur. No, he says
the more strict opinion. You wouldn't have thought that by תחתון tachton
it sounds like he's being lenient or whatever. But it has a
ברייתא baraita that says that no, the crust that's facing the oven,
that's facing the wall has to crust over, so that is a
later stage and only then are we not concerned of you keeping
it on the fire when it's שבת. Shabbat. Okay, משלשלין את הפסח.
Meshalshelin et hapesach. Now, the one exception is the קרבן פסח. Korban
Pesach. You can lower that into the oven right before שבת, Shabbat,
even though it's not yet roasted.
מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason? משום דבני חבורה זריזין הן.
mishum dibnei chaburah zrizin hein. The people of the group are going
to be very careful. So now this is a question, is that
specifically because they're all there focused on bringing the קרבן פסח, Korban
Pesach, so they're sort of, you know, their religious sensitivity is heightened?
Is it specifically בני חבורה bnei chaburah or is it a general
issue that when you have a group of people, you assume at
least one person will remember and remind other people? As I said,
there's a משנה Mishnah way at the end of מסכת שבת Masechet
Shabbat that says one person can't take a bath on
שבת. Shabbos. מנהג אשכנז minhag Ashkenaz is never take a bath regardless,
but in the גמרא Gemara it was only concern about squeezing the
towels. Assume the water was not heated up, was not heated up,
whatever, we'll talk about it later. But anyway, one person cannot take
a bath even if he uses ten towels because we're afraid it'll
lead to squeezing towels. But ten people can take a bath even
if they're sharing one towel, even obviously the towel gets a lot
wetter and there's greater concern of squeezing. Why? Because they'll remind one
another. So at least one person there will have their wits about
them and say, 'Hey, you can't be squeezing, it's שבת'. Shabbat Okay,
so normally there's an idea that if there's a group of people
doing this... we had that also by reading by the candlelight, remember?
And the חזן chazzan having the kids read by the candlelight. All
the time there's a question, is it a particular type of a
group that we say will be heightened awareness or any group we
say at least one person will be on top of it? But
it is a recurring theme that some of these גזירות gezeirot of
that you'll forget don't apply in a group. So that's why the
קרבן פסח Korban Pesach is okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, הא
לאו הכי לא? ha lav hachi lo? Are you telling me that
without that it would not be okay? ואמר מר, Ve'amar mar, didn't
we say just like two days ago, גדיא, Gadya, if you're talking
about a goat, which is, right, קרבן פסח Korban Pesach often could
be a goat, בין שרי בין לא שרי שפיר דמי, bein shari
bein lo shari shapir dami, whether the oven is sealed or not
sealed, you can put it on the fire right before שבת, Shabbat,
and we're not concerned that you will stir the coals because you'd
have to open up the oven and the air would be bad
for the goat. So it seems like even if it's one person
doing it, if you're roasting a goat, it's not a problem, we're
not afraid you'll open the oven. So the גמרא Gemara says, no,
התם מנתח הכא לא מנתח. Hatam mentach hacha lo mentach. There it
is chopped up into pieces. And because it's chopped up into pieces,
the air will be damaging to it, like a lot of surface
area is exposed. And there you keep the oven, the top of
the oven sealed. Here it's a whole big piece, your קרבן פסח,
Korban Pesach, whole point is you don't, it's all the entire thing
is on the spit at once. Since the entire thing is on
the spit at once, and actually I bet before you read this
משנה, Mishnah, you probably assumed that they would roast the קרבן פסח
Korban Pesach in open air, right? This משנה Mishnah is a חידוש
chiddush that you put it into an oven. So the point is
you're not so afraid of exposing it to air because it is
all one big, it's all, you know, one big goat being roasted
as whole and it's not so, it doesn't have the type of
surface area that it would be when it's chopped up into pieces.
Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. So that's in
terms of the exception of the קרבן פסח Korban Pesach because it's
a group and so on. ומאחיזין את האור. Umachizin et ha'ur. Now
when it comes to lighting the fire. itself, so in the בית
המוקד Beit ha-Moked in the בית המקדש, Beit ha-Mikdash, they could just
get the fire started. Outside the בית המקדש, Beit ha-Mikdash, it had
to seize most of the wood. So, מנא הני מילי, minan milei,
where do you get this idea that you could be more lenient
in the
בית המקדש? Beit ha-Mikdash? אמר רב הונא: Amar Rav Huna: לא תבערו
אש בכל משבתיכם ביום השבת. Lo teva'aru esh bekhol moshvoteikhem beyom ha-Shabbat.
Do not burn a fire in all of your dwelling places on
the Shabbat. So the דרשה drasha is the
following: בכל משבתיכם Bekhol moshvoteikhem you can't make an אש esh where
you dwell, אבל אתה מבעיר במדורת בית המוקד, aval ata mavir bimdurat
beit ha-moked, you can make a fire in this place in the
room in the בית המקדש. Beit ha-Mikdash. It's not a dwelling place,
it's the place, it's the משכן, Mishkan, it's the בית המקדש. Beit
ha-Mikdash. So the גמרא Gemara says: מתקיף לה רב חסדא, matkif la
Rav Chisda, Rav Chisda said, אי הכי, i hakhi, אפילו בשבת נמי.
afillu be-Shabbat nami. If that's true, then it's not just a leniency
for before Shabbat, then you're telling me that you can make a
fire even on Shabbat. Now we know you can do מלאכה melakha
in the בית המקדש Beit ha-Mikdash on Shabbat, but for the sake
of קרבנות korbanot and even there, only קרבנות korbanot that must be
brought on Shabbat, only קרבן korban that's במועדו be-mo'ado in its time.
You cannot bring optional קרבנות korbanot and you cannot do מלאכות melakhot
for the כהנים Kohanim for, you know, you can only do it
for the sake of directly bringing the קרבן. korban. So that's the
challenge. What are you doing with the פסוק? pasuk? I mean, if
it were, if you were really, if you were serious about the
פסוק, pasuk, you should be allowed to make a fire לכתחילה lekhatchila
and obviously you can't do that. So, I mean, you can only
do it directly for the קרבן. korban. So, אלא אמר רב חסדא:
ella amar Rav Chisda: קרא כי אתא למשרי אברים ופדרים הוא דאתא.
kra ki ata lemishrei evarim upedarim hu de-ata. The פסוק pasuk is
coming to allow a different thing. The פסוק pasuk is coming to
allow burning the fats and the pieces. Meaning, yes, we already know
you can bring, let's say, the קרבן תמיד Korban Tamid and the
מוסף Musaf on Shabbat, but how about burning the fats? The fats,
now there's a question in תוספות Tosafot which fats? Either it means
the fats of קרבנות korbanot you brought yesterday, and that's a big
חידוש chiddush that you can burn the fats of yesterday's קרבן korban
on Shabbat. תוספות Tosafot is not so clear that that's true; he
goes back and forth with that possibility. Or the limbs and the
fats of the תמיד Tamid and the מוסף, Musaf, but you don't
have to burn those on Shabbat, you could wait till מוצאי שבת.
Motza'ei Shabbat. But nevertheless, we learn from those, from that פסוק, pasuk,
that one or both of those is allowed. But that's directly about
a קרבן. korban. To make a fire for the כהנים, Kohanim, that's
not allowed; that's חילול שבת. chilul Shabbat. So why are we more
lenient to just get it started? כהנים זריזים הם, Kohanim zrizim hem,
because look, כהנים Kohanim will be careful, the same way בני חבורה
זריזים הם. benei chabura zrizim hem. There's also another general principle of
אין שבות במקדש, ein shvut ba-Mikdash, that rabbinic restrictions we often give
a pass in the בית המקדש Beit ha-Mikdash about Shabbat because we
have to give כהנים Kohanim more latitude. So basically, yes, we're not
going to let you make a fire לכתחילה, lekhatchila, you know, on
Shabbat for the כהנים, Kohanim, but when ערב שבת, Erev Shabbat, we'll
say it's enough just to get the fire started. The כהנים Kohanim
will be very careful and very on top of it, and they'll
be sure not to stir the fire. So therefore we don't have
to worry, the same way we would when we make it sort
of globally permitted for everybody. You know, there's some people that are
more careful, some people less careful. There we're going to say the
fire, but if you want to start a fire ערב שבת, Erev
Shabbat, it has to seize most of the wood. But for the
כהנים, Kohanim, it'll be enough that it just gets started. Okay, and
now we're going to look at the outside of the בית המקדש.
Beit ha-Mikdash. ובגבולין כדי שתאחוז האור, Uvigvulin kedei she-tochoz ha-ur, excuse me,
ובגבולין כדי שתאחוז האור. Uvigvulin kedei she-tochoz ha-ur.
So the גמרא Gemara says now: מאי רובא? mai ruba?
What does it mean most until the fire takes, seizes most of
it? So, אמר רב: Amar Rav: רוב כל אחד ואחד, rov kol
echad ve-echad, most of each stick has to be on fire
if you're making this bonfire ערב שבת Erev Shabbat or whatever. ושמואל
אמר: Ushmuel amar: כדי שלא יאמרו הבו עצים ונניח תחתיהם. kedei she-lo
yomru havu etzim venaniach tachteihem. שמואל Shmuel has a very much more
practical explanation. It's not like quantitative, but you really understand שמואל's Shmuel
position if anybody has ever made a bonfire. When it gets to
the stage where you don't say we need more twigs to get
it going, okay? Once it's got to the point where you say,
okay, now it's fine, now it'll go by itself, then you're okay.
תני דבי רבי חייא לסיועיה לשמואל. Tanei debei Rabbi Chiyya lesiyu'ei le-Shmuel.
רבי חייא Rabbi Chiyya taught to support שמואל: Shmuel: כדי שתהא שלהבת
עולה מאליה. kedei she-tehei shalhevet ola me'eleha. This is a very nice
idea about how they would light the מנורה Menorah in the בית
המקדש. Beit ha-Mikdash. It says that they would light it until the
point that the flame would rise up on its own, that you
would not need to be fiddling with it or adjusting it; now
it will just rise up on its own. Now of course that's
about lighting in the בית המקדש, Beit ha-Mikdash, it's not about a
concern about fiddling on Shabbat, but the point is we don't need
maybe a quantitative definition. When it's at the stage that it's going
by itself, then you're, then that's what suffices there, that's what should
suffice here. ולא שתהא שלהבת עולה על ידי דבר אחר, Velo she-tehei
shalhevet ola al yedei davar acher, and not, it's not enough to
light the מנורה Menorah to the point that you still need to
sort of get the flame going by adding something else. Okay, so
here too, once it's going by itself, then you're done. Now, עץ
יחידי, etz yechidi,
let's say you have an individual stick that you're lighting on Shabbat.
So how much does it have to catch fire so you don't
have to worry about it? רב אמר: Rav amar: רוב עביו, rov
obyov, most of its thickness. ואמרי לה: ve-amri la: ברוב היקפו. berov
hekefo. And some say most of its circumference. So thickness presumably means,
you know, the length of the stick, it's not so clear though,
anyway, and the circumference means all the way around. אמר רב פפא...
Amar Rav Papa... הלכך, hilkach, therefore, בעינן רוב עביו ובעינן רוב היקפו.
beinan rov avyav uveinan rov hekefo.
Since we don't know which way to go, we'll be strict both
ways. Okay, so if it's one stick, you need it to be
both the thickness and the circumference. אמר רב פפא Amar Rav Pappa
הלכך, hilkach, I just said that. כתנאי, ketannai, this is the debate
of Tannaim. רבי חייא אמר Rabbi Chiyya amar כדי שישחית העץ ממלאכת
האומן, kedei sheyishacheit ha'etz mimlechet ha'uman, that it has to be so
much caught fire that it can no longer, the stick can no
longer be used for some like for, you know, for a craftsperson,
for a craftsman, it's no longer useful in some other capacity.
ורבי יהודה בן בתירא אומר VeRabbi Yehuda ben Beteira omer כדי שתאחוז
האש משני צדדין, kedei shetochaz ha'eish mishnei tzedadin, that the fire has
to catch on both sides of the stick. ואף על פי שאין
ראיה לדבר זכר לדבר, Ve'af al pi she'ein raya ladavar zeicher ladavar,
although there's not a proof, there's a hint to this. The Pasuk
in Yechezkel says את שני קצותיו אכלה האש, et shnei ktzotav achla
ha'eish, the fire burnt the two edges of this, of the stick,
ותוכו נחר היצלח למלאכה, vetocho nachar hayitzlach limlacha, and the middle was
dried up, can it be used for any type of work? So
now that sounds similar to the earlier position of it's no longer
useful for work. But anyway, the Gemara understands that this is a
debate, that the one that says that, it's not exactly totally clear
which one goes which way, but anyway, Rashi, let me just check
Rashi. He says,
yeah,
Rashi says the opinion about that the fire is burning on both
sides is the one that says רוב היקפו, rov hekefo, most of
its circumference, whereas the one that says that it's so much destroyed
that it can no longer be used for a craft is the
one that says most of its thickness. And I have to be
honest, I'm not really clear to me how those things exactly correspond.
But anyway, those are the different opinions about how much one stick
has to catch fire in order for you not to have to
worry about it when Shabbos begins. Okay, now that the Gemara has
this little, is talking about fire, we have a little bit of
a slight digression. והאח לפניו מבוערת, veha'ach lefanav mevo'aret,
the fire was burning in front of him. This is a Pasuk
in Yirmiyahu which is talking about Yehoyakim when he burnt the Megilla
of Eicha. They read this Megilla about all of the destruction of
Yerushalayim and he didn't want to accept it, so he threw it
into the fire. So מאי אח? mai ach? What does it mean,
the ach? I just translated it as fire, but by context, but
what does it mean? אמר רב Amar Rav אחוונא, achvana, אחוונא, achvana,
which means according to Rashi, and we'll see actually in the beginning
of the next Perek, it means
ערבה, arava, a willow. Thank you. So somehow these are words for
like willow branches. ושמואל אמר VeShmuel amar עצים שנדלקו באחוונא. eitzim shenidliku
be'achvana. No, it means that sticks of wood that
were burned in brotherhood. What does it mean brotherhood? It means if
you look at Rashi כל העצים נדלקים זה מזה קטן מדליק הגדול.
kol ha'eitzim nidlakim zeh mizeh katan madlik hagadol. So it means sort
of like some type of a, you know, a pile of wood
where because they're all together one lights from the other, so more
like a little, you know, a little bonfire. Okay. ההוא
דאמר להו Hahu de'amar lehu מאן בעי אחוונא? man ba'ei achvana? There
was somebody who's going around saying who wants achvana? ואשתכח ערבתא, ve'ishtakach
arvassa, and they found out that he was selling aravas. So you
see that ach or at least achvana means aravas, so maybe ach
also means aravas. אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, back to Halacha.
קנים אין צריכים רוב, kanim ein tzrichim rov, אגדן צריכים רוב. agdan
tzrichim rov. If you have just twigs, then you do not need
the fire to catch on the majority of them. Twigs burn easily
and therefore it's not exactly clear how much, but a little bit
should be okay erev Shabbat. However, agdan, if you bundle them, then
tzrichim rov, then because it's harder for the fire you know to
get in between because it's all tightly bundled, so then you need
the fire to grab onto most of it. גרעינים, garinim, if you
have seeds, Rashi says this means like seeds of a date, I
guess they would use them as firewood, ein tzrichim rov, then also
they can because there's maybe a lot of surface area.
Right. You don't need, yeah, you don't need the majority. נתנם בכותלות,
netanam bechutalot, if you put them in baskets and again there's less
surface area and they're more packed, tzrichim rov, then you need the
majority to catch on. מתיב לה רב חסדא Mative lei Rav Chisda
אדרבה. aderaba. Rav Chisda has the opposite. איפכא מסתברא, ipcha mistabra, the
opposite makes sense. קנים, kanim, if you have sticks, מבדרן. mevadran. If
they're separated out, they're scattered out, so then they don't light from
one another, each one is by itself, so maybe one catching can
easily more fizzle out, it doesn't have another thing to keep it
you know to re-light it.
אגדן לא מבדרן. agdan lo mevadran. If you bundle them together then
they're not separate and then they will be, you know, if one
thing is going out the other thing will light it. So he
thinks that if they're all bundled together you know then it'll be
easier for them to stay aflame. It's so funny they're making like
a logical argument which you'd want them to like run some test
but okay. גרעינים, garinim, similar by date stones, mevadran, they're separate so
they'll burn out easily.
נתנם בכותלות, netanam bechutalot, lo mevadran, they're not scattered, so maybe they'll
burn more easily. It's the exact opposite of what you said. איתמר
נמי, Itmar nami, so fact similarly top of Chaf Amud Bet, אמר
רב כהנא. Amar Rav Kahana. כהנא, kahana, now this is not exactly,
there's a whole question about what the גירסא girsa is, cause according
to our גירסא, girsa, it's actually a split vote. קנים שאגדן, kanim
she'agadan, צריכים רוב, tzrichim rov, if you have sticks if you bundle
them, then it's harder for them to stay to stay alit, and
therefore you need them to be the majority caught fire for it
to be okay ערב שבת. erev shabbos. לא אגדן, lo agdan, if
they're not bundled, אין צריכים רוב, ein tzrichim rov, then you don't
need that they'll they'll catch flame and stay aflame more easily. And
גרעינין, gar'inim, the the pits of the dates is the opposite, צריכים
רוב, tzrichim rov, by themselves they need the majority to catch fire
to stay alit. נתנן בכחלות, nasanan bechutalos, if they're in a basket,
אין צריכים רוב, ein tzrichim rov, then they don't, then it actually
stays alit better. So according to this it's not a תניא נמי
הכי, tanyami hachi, it's a split vote. It says the sticks will
stay aflame easier separate and the date pits will stay aflame easier
together. Anyway you see there's a lot of א alephs and ב,
bais, there's a lot of different גירסאות girsos here that have very,
you know, that come out all different ways in terms of what
this ברייתא braisa is saying. Okay. תני רב יוסף, tani rav yosef,
ארבע מדורות אין צריכים רוב. arba meduros ein tzrichim rov. There are
four types of bonfires that you do not need or or whatever
flames you do not need a majority again similar to some of
these other issues about twigs and whatnot that we say or like
the end of the משנה mishna that said about charcoal, there are
four scenarios where things once they're on fire will stay aflame and
you don't have to worry about it ערב שבת. erev shabbos. What
are they? של זפת, shel zefes, if it's made of like tar
or pitch, which apparently is like a very flammable. ושל גפרית, veshel
gofris, sulfur. So ושל גבינה, veshel gvina, now that's bizarre. Cheese? Who's
burning cheese? So if you look at the side here the ג
gimmel and the גרא, gra, he says the גירסא girsa is קירא,
kira, which is which is like gourds. I don't know, do gourds
burn well? Who knows?
What did your what did your English guys say? Do they have
any interesting suggestions?
Dry cheese.
Dry cheese. You can burn dry cheese and it'll stay it'll stay
as fire?
Never heard of it.
All right, anyway, or whatever. All right. ושל רבב, veshel revav, רבב
revav is some type of a liquid flammable object. So I was
joking in the משנה mishna I said what about lighter fluid, so
that's essentially what רבב revav is. רש"י rashi says it's like wax,
like molten like liquefied wax or oil and so on. So these
types of things are not an issue. דתניא de-rasnisa תנן, tanan, in
a ברייתא braisa we taught, אף של קש ושל גבבא, af shel
kash veshel gvava, even a stubble and straw, you know, are things
I mean they'll go out pretty quickly but you're not going to
need to fiddle with it, it'll burn well, it'll burn a little
bit too well. What?
Segue into the next chapter.
Exactly. אמר רבי יוחנן, amar rabbi yochanan, the whole thing is a
segue into the next chapter. אמר רבי יוחנן, amar rabbi yochanan, עצים
של בבל אין צריכים רוב. eitzim shel bavel ein tzrichim rov.
The the wood in בבל bavel does not need רוב rov maybe
again it's very oily or something and it stays aflame or maybe
it's very dry. מתיב ליה רב יוסף מאי היא? mas'kif lah rav
yosef mai hi?
What are you talking about? אילימא סילתי, eileima silty, if you're referring
to סילתי, silty, so
I don't know how they translate סילתי. silty.
Thin very strips.
Just thin strips. Okay fine. If you mean thin strips, I mean
that's what רש"י rashi says, לאחר שעשו עצים דקות. l'achar she'asu eitzim
dakos. I was wondering if it had some other explanation. Anyway if
you're talking about thin strips, השתא פתילה אמר עולא המדליק צריך שידליק
ברוב היוצא, hashta psila amar ulla hamadlik tzarich she-yadlik berov hayotze, סילתי
מיבעיא? silty mibaya?
So if you say thin strips, well עולא's ulla going to tell
us in the next פרק perek that when you are lighting a
wick you have to make sure of of a oil lamp, you
have to make sure that the majority of the wick that's exposed,
right? Look if you look at that picture on the beginning of
the of the שניים אוחזין, shnayim ohachoz, you see what those oil
lamps look like. You'd have the oil there and a little wick
would come out from like the mouth from the mouth. So he
says you have to make sure that most of that exposed wick
is burning on ערב שבת. erev shabbos. So you need רוב rov
at least of the exposed wick. So how should a thin strip
of wood be more lenient than a wick that's made for drawing
the oil and even so עולא ulla says you need a majority?
סילתי מיבעיא? silty mibaya? So would there be any question that it
should be the same by a thin strip of wood? אלא אמר
רב יוסף, ella amar rav yosef, שוכא דארזא. shucha de-arza. What we're
talking about is some type of like of a woolly substance and
we're going to see this in a minute in the next פרק,
perek, by a cedar tree that's between like the bark and the
actual trunk itself, and this was you know very flammable. Okay.
So therefore you don't need רוב. rov. Once you just get the
fire started then it's okay ערב שבת erev shabbos where we know
that it'll burn and you're not going to fiddle with it.
Why is it any different than a wick?
Yeah that's a good point I mean cause you would think that
wicks also are made that way but presumably I don't know if
everyone has ever you know when you light שבת shabbos candle חנוכה
chanukah candles if you use oil you know sometimes that after you've
lit the wick it does go out. So even though the wick
is made for drawing it, look we are a little bit what
do you call it spoiled
because candle wicks are coated with wax. So that's why they burn
so easily and they stay burning but if you just have you
know the actual wick
itself the whatever whatever the material is you sometimes it doesn't stay
lit. So that's what he's saying if it was just a stick
it shouldn't be better than a wick. If it's something like this
שוכא דארזא shucha de-arza which is like this sort of woolly stuff
between and the bark and the trunk of the cedar tree, that
is very flammable, and that you don't need רוב. rov. רמי בר
אבא אמר זזא. Rami bar Abba amar zaza. He says זזא. zaza.
I don't know, רש''י Rashi says it's מושא, musha, which doesn't mean
anything to us. What does it say? איזוב? ezov? Moss? Oh, or
איזוב ezov was the... okay, that's interesting. His... what, hyssop, right? Okay,
so anyway, so this is all going to be הדרן עלך יציאות
שבת. hadran alach yetziyos shabbos. So that is the end of that
פרק. perek. As we saw, once we got through the י''ח דבר,
yud chet davar, there was most of the פרק perek was about...
it started with carrying, it introduced the idea of not doing things
late in the day, you'll forget, but that was in a normal
week day, you'll forget to דאוון daven מנחה, Mincha, and then it
was all about doing things ערב שבת erev shabbos leading into שבת.
shabbos. Okay, and what it ended with, what it almost started and
ended, not exactly started, but near the beginning was reading by candlelight,
you'll tip it, and that's on שבת shabbos itself, and the end
was lighting a fire and having... roasting things and whatever on שבת,
shabbos, don't do that unless it's going well cause you'll come to
fiddle with it. And that is a perfect segue into the next
פרק, perek, which is במה מדליקין. bameh madlikin. Okay, which is what
do you use for your candles, for your... for your lamps on
שבת. shabbos. What types of wicks, what types of oil. And the
concern here is that if it's not a good wick, or it's
not a good oil, then it will be sputtering and it won't
be burning evenly and you will come to tip. So even if
you're not reading by the candlelight, even if you're just having dinner
by the candlelight, if it's not burning well, we're afraid you will
fiddle with it and it's a really a straight continuation from the
types of concerns from the previous פרק. perek. And actually some of
the materials we were just talking about about the... about the ערבה,
aravah, the willow, and the... and the wool of the... of the
cedar tree, that will be repeated here. I did want to say
one though word of introduction, which is the simple reading of all
this משנה Mishna is that there's no such thing as a מצוה
mitzvah of lighting candles ערב שבת. erev shabbos. It was just a
reality that of course, you know, you didn't have electric lights. So
if you wanted to see in the house Friday night, you'd have
to light candles ערב שבת. erev shabbos. That's how you had light.
And now, it wasn't so much of an issue during the week
because during the week if you wanted to see, you'd light it
at nighttime. And actually according... it seems like there's good evidence that
mostly they would have their meals before dark during the week. Actually
some of that came up in the beginning of ברכות. Berachot. But
on שבת, shabbos, you'd... you're having your meal after dark and you...
you can't light it on שבת, shabbos, so you light it ערב
שבת. erev shabbos. And this is just dealing with the realities, given
the reality that you're lighting candles ערב שבת erev shabbos in order
that you'll have light Friday night, what types of wicks and oils
do you have to use? The same way if you're putting something
on the fire ערב שבת, erev shabbos, what do you have to
do to make sure you're not going to fiddle with the fire?
That being said, in the גמרא, Gemara, it becomes clear that at
a certain stage in the גמרא Gemara and then in the ראשונים,
Rishonim, it crystallizes as a מצוה. mitzvah. There are some actual historians
that want to argue that even at the time of the משנה,
Mishna, it was already seen, if not a formalized מצוה mitzvah with
a ברכה, bracha, but seen as somehow as something of like a
ritual... an act of ritual significance, not just a way of turning
on the lights ערב שבת. erev shabbos. Because there's good evidence from
like non-Jewish sources, but other sources of... from pagan sources or whatever
that are talking about the Jewish practice of lighting candles ערב שבת.
erev shabbos. So actually, now again, it doesn't really prove fully, but
there are some arguments that even at the time of the משנה,
Mishna, it was already seen of... well, okay, any... well, why is
that? I mean, first of all, it could have started as just
practical, make sure there's light, but then it, you know, once everybody
is doing it, it becomes ritualized and lighting candles often was associated,
you know, with a like a special religious type of an experience.
People like... some people have the כלה Kallah candles at weddings, you
know, when you walk them down, so you can understand how it
gets religious significance. But anyway, it's... but we will see as we're
doing this פרק, perek, the question about when did it really crystallize
as a מצוה. mitzvah. And then it became a woman's מצוה, mitzvah,
right, and the משנה Mishna at the end about a person saying
in the house and a woman have to be careful with it.
So that, read in a certain way, it's possible to understand that
in the משנה Mishna already it's a מצוה, mitzvah, but there's some
question when exactly that crystallized. But certainly the first concern, what can
you use for candlelight, is a question about the concern that you
will come to fiddle with it. We will see as we do
the פרק perek to what degree it became a מצוה. mitzvah. I
did want to say one other word of introduction, which is later,
you know, everybody knows, right, that the Karaites, right, would not have
fire going from ערב שבת, erev shabbos, would not have their food
cooking from ערב שבת erev shabbos onto שבת. shabbos. לא תבערו אש
בכל משבתיכם ביום השבת. Lo teva'aru esh bechol moshvoteichem beyom haShabbat.
They interpreted it to mean a fire can't be burning on שבת
shabbos even if it started ערב שבת. erev shabbos. And that's why,
you know, the idea of having like טשולנט cholent became an important
like institution to prove against the Karaites, you know, because you're having
it burning... the fire burning on שבת. shabbos. So lighting candles also
was very important in these sort of Karaites polemic of lighting the
candles ערב שבת erev shabbos and burning on שבת. shabbos. It is
not clear that often there's an assumption
that
Karaites... The first we know that there were those that said you're
not allowed to do it was in the Karaite period, which is
in the גאוניק Geonic period. And it is in that period where
the institution developed, the practice developed to say במה מדליקין Bameh Madlikin
ערב שבת Erev Shabbat as a way of sort of underscoring that
you can light these candles on שבת Shabbat and as part of
the Karaite polemic there developed this institution of saying במה מדליקין Bameh
Madlikin as we do say in a lot of נוסחאות nuschaot on
ערב שבת. Erev Shabbat. And I actually wanted to share with you,
I don't know, it came out a little microscopic. Anyway, there's only
like a few copies here, but in some in some manuscripts in
the גניזה, Geniza, they found they found the following ברכה bracha that
preceded the saying of במה מדליקין Bameh Madlikin from the גאוניק Geonic
period. And I'll read it to you. ברוך אתה ה' אלהינו מלך
העולם אשר בחר בחכמים ותלמידיהם ונתן להם תורה מהר סיני על ידי
משה רבינו, Baruch Atah Hashem Elokeinu Melech Ha'olam asher bachar bachachamim v'talmideihem
v'natan lahem Torah meHar Sinai al yedei Moshe Rabbeinu, you're getting the
sort of Karaite polemic here, וצוה אותם לקרוא בתורה ולשנות בתלמוד ובהלכה
לקנות חיי עולמים ובחר במשה עבדו בכל הנביאים ואחריו בחר ביהושע תלמידו
ובשבעים זקנים ונביאים ובחכמים ובתלמידיהם וצוה אותם בשמירת שבת ובהדלקת נר של
שבת v'tzivah otam likro baTorah v'lishnot baTalmud uvaHalacha liknot chayei olamim uvachar
beMoshe avdo bechol hanevi'im v'acharayiv bachar biYehoshua talmido uvishivim zekenim unevei'im uvachachamim
v'talmideihem v'tzivah otam bishmirat Shabbat uv'hadlakat ner shel Shabbat and then במה
מדליקין. Bameh Madlikin.
So a very extensive ברכה bracha of God giving us the תורה
Torah at הר סיני Har Sinai and the tradition that passed through
the sages, רבניק, Rabbinic, the רבניק Rabbinic tradition and that's and the
מצוה mitzvah of lighting the candles on שבת Shabbat and then they
say במה מדליקין. Bameh Madlikin. So clearly if if it wasn't crystallized
as a מצוה mitzvah in the time of the גמרא Gemara or
in the time of the משנה, Mishna, it certainly became one in
the גאוניק Geonic period with במה מדליקין Bameh Madlikin with a ברכה
bracha on במה מדליקין. Bameh Madlikin. A ברכה bracha you don't have
in the משנה Mishna a ברכה bracha on the candles. The first
description of a ברכה bracha on the candles comes up in the
גאוניק Geonic period. So and again, interesting in terms of the Karaite
polemic as well.
Yes. As long as we say במה מדליקין Bameh Madlikin as late
as we do, shouldn't you say that before you accept שבת? Shabbat?
Yeah, what can I tell you? Yes. Okay, so maybe it's a
proof that we should be דאווענינג davening קבלת שבת Kabbalat Shabbat early.
So was this ברכה bracha
said at some point early?
No, they would say it in the דאווענינג davening right before no,
I think not not before the lighting, I think they'd say it
in דאווענינג davening before they read the במה מדליקין Bameh Madlikin because
this is a נוסח nusach right after that in the סידור Siddur
it had the במה מדליקין. Bameh Madlikin. Okay. All right, so anyway,
let's take a look now now with that introduction, let's start the
second פרק. perek. במה מדליקין ובמה אין מדליקין. Bameh madlikin uvameh ein
madlikin. What can you light with and what can you not light?
אין מדליקין Ein madlikin so it starts with the last. Sometimes תוספות
Tosafot points out it goes to the it says what yes what
no, sometimes it starts with the first, sometimes it starts with the
second. Also, you know, there's a question about which is the shorter
list. You're going to list the things is the shorter list for
what you can use or what you can't use. Okay, so here's
going to list what you can't use. אין מדליקין Ein madlikin you
can't use לא בלכש lo velechesh not לכש lechesh some have the
גירסא girsa לגש. leges. Okay, I won't translate this because the גמרא
Gemara will translate all these. ולא בחוסן v'lo vechosen or חוסן chosen
ולא בכלך v'lo vechlach that at least is assumed to be silk
ולא בפתילת האידן v'lo biftilat ha'idan or not the string of אידן,
idan, we'll see what that is, ולא בפתילת המדבר v'lo biftilat hamidbar
or the string of the מדבר midbar ולא בירוקה שעל פני המים
v'lo beyaroka she'al pnei hamayim the green on the water presumably moss.
So wait none of these can be used as wicks. We're talking
about wicks. Okay.
What you said before about the זאזא zaza which was above, which
you translated as moss? All right, yeah. So then that apparently burnt
very quickly. So what was that used for?
So then that's why it can't be a wick. Okay, it could
be a fuel. Okay, just hold on. ולא v'lo so all of
that is things you can't use as wicks. Now we are switching
to although there is not a clear separation, we're switching to fuels.
ולא בזפת v'lo vezeft you can't use tar ולא בשעוה v'lo vesha'avah
or a wax ולא בשמן קיק v'lo veshemen kik and not with
sunflower oil ולא בשמן שריפה v'lo veshemen sreifah or burnt oil, what
does that mean? We'll see in the גמרא Gemara that's a specific
הלכתיק halakhic status. ולא באליה v'lo ve'alyah not with the fat tail
of a sheep ולא בחלב v'lo vechelev and not with the fat
of the suet of the forbidden fat of an animal. I mean
you're allowed to get הנאה hana'ah but you can't use it here
for fuel.
Suet? Yes,
S-U-E-T. Okay. נחום המדי אומר Nachum HaMadi omer Nachum HaMadi says מדליקין
בחלב מבושל madlikin bechelev mevushal you can use it if it's been
cooked then it will burn well. וחכמים אומרים אחד מבושל ואחד שאינו
מבושל v'Chachamim omrim echad mevushal v'echad she'eino mevushal whether cooked or uncooked
אין מדליקין בו ein madlikin bo you can't use it. So that's
about fuels. Now as Michael said and we'll see in the גמרא,
Gemara, you know the גמרא Gemara a minute ago said some of
this stuff that seems like you can't use as wicks, the גמרא
Gemara a minute ago said if you start burning it you don't
have to worry about רוב rov because it'll burn well. It's true,
but there's you want for characteristic of a wick, you want it
to not be able to be able to
burn with ease but also not to be able to burn up
too quickly, right? If a wick burns up too quickly it doesn't
do any good either. So anyway so part of this might be
that it might have been okay as we just read for fuel,
might have even been better for fuel but not ideal for a
wick. Okay, so we'll see it as we go through one by
one. Let's look at the גמרא. Gemara. What's לכש? lechesh? So it
says שוכא דארזא. shucha d'arza. There you go, exactly what we said
a minute ago. What's לכש? Lachash? So it says שוחא דארזא. Shucha
d'arza. There you go. That'd be what we said a minute ago,
that wool in the between the sort of bark and the and
the and the trunk of a cedar tree. So the גמרא Gemara
before said it burns very easily, it's not an issue of רוב,
rov, but it can't be used for a wick, presumably yeah, it
does burn too easily, and therefore it'll burn out, and that's a
concern. So the גמרא Gemara says שוחא דארזא עץ בעלמא הוא. Shucha
d'arza etz be'alma hu. Wait a minute, the גמרא Gemara says it
thought it meant like a twig from a cedar tree. That's a
stick. Of course you're not using a stick as a wick. So
no, בעמרניתא דאית בה, be'amrnisa de'it ba, the woolly part that is
like that is in it, meaning that's this woolly substance that's between
the bark and the trunk. Yeah, the fiber. Okay. ולא בחוסן. velo
be'chosen. What's חוסן? chosen? So אמר רב יוסף נעורת של פשתן, Amar
Rav Yosef ne'oret shel pishtan, that is
like strings of flax,
the combings of flax. אמר ליה אביי, Amar leh Abaye, אביי Abaye
says והא כתיב והיה
החסון לנעורת, veha ketiv vehaya hechason lene'oret, לנעורת lene'urat I guess, that
the חוסן chosen and the חסונא chasuna I guess will turn into
נעורת, ne'oret, so you see חסון chasun is not the combed flax,
it's something else. אלא אמר אביי, Ella amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says
כיתנא דדייק ולא נפיץ. kitna de'dayek velo nafitz. It's
uncombed flax, flax that's been beaten and has not been combed yet.
So the husks of the flax have not yet been removed, and
because it's the flax still has these husks in it, it will
burn unevenly. So if you want to use flax as a wick,
you would have to first comb the flax, not this uncombed flax.
Yes.
Because over here we said oh, this is בעמרניתא דאית בה, be'amrnisa
de'it ba, but we didn't say that on top, so is that
two different things?
I don't know. Okay, ולא בכלך, velo be'clach, and not with silk.
So again, silk presumably the problem is that it burns too quickly,
it just burns up, right? אמר שמואל שאלתי לכל נחותי ימא, Amar
Shmuel she'alti lechol ne'chutei yama, I asked all those that would go
down to the sea, the
seafarers, ואמרו לי כולכא שמיה. ve'amru li kulcha shemei. Oh it's called
כולכא. kulcha. Well that helps, כלך clach is כולכא. kulcha. I mean
that's basically just the straight Aramaic translation without explaining it. So by
the way, I was reading a little bit about this in this
ספרי משנה Sifrai Mishnah version, that apparently that silk was imported from
China and it was imported into ארץ ישראל. Eretz Yisrael. By the
way, they were also quite interesting when we were learning before about
the whole ways about making about starting processes before שבת Shabbos and
about dyeing the wool and about making the flax. I was not
aware of this, apparently
ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael was one of the prime sources of quality
textiles in the Roman Empire, and they were well known for their
wool and for their flax. So actually when it mentioned that in
the previous משנה, Mishnah, these were like primary exports of ישראל Yisrael
and it was really well developed economy.
But silk was imported from China. Now it was imported by sea
and it was imported into ישראל. Yisrael. And they sort of point
out that when שמואל Shmuel says I asked the seafarers that was
in בבל Bavel they did not get things by the sea. So
he says that that was actually a borrowed expression, it wasn't a
literal expression by שמואל. Shmuel. In ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael they actually
had a whole trade by the Mediterranean and so on.
The Silk Road. Yeah, from בבל Bavel I mean. Oh it'll cut
through בבל? Bavel?
I'm not sure if it did.
I think it came across. It was further north and I don't
know how developed it was at that point.
Right. Interesting. All right. So anyway, so that's what he said.
So
רב יצחק בר זעירא אמר, Rav Yitzchak bar Ze'ira amar, גושקרא. gushkera.
Well that helps. So apparently גושקרא gushkera is also some type of
silk. I saw that Steinsaltz says it's something about the cocoon of
the silkworm. Yeah, some type of thing also. Okay, so fine.
רש"י Rashi says it's some type of a dross of the silk.
I don't know what that means. But anyway, oh no, רש"י Rashi
says I'm sorry, רש"י Rashi says הוא בית התולעת. hu beit hatola'at.
Right, רש"י Rashi does say that, that's where they're getting it from.
So רש"י Rashi says that it's the house of the worm. Yes,
I'm sorry. Silk is very
expensive, why would anybody think about using it? Well that's maybe why
the concern is maybe it's the stuff that's thrown out of the
process, like so that's why they're suggesting. Right, it's a good point,
like real silk who would use, but
this is the stuff that's maybe the discarded part of the process,
which is why it's like the cocoon of the silkworm.
But it's worth noting over here in the ArtScroll saying for this
כולכא kulcha that it's not silk, some woolly substance found on stones
in the sea. So that's why they're asking the seafarers because Interesting.
Who do they quote that says that?
They say the שנות אליהו. Shenot Eliyahu. All right.
All right. That's the גרא's Gra interpretation. All right.
רבין ואביי הוו יתבי קמיה דרבנא נחמיה. Ravin ve'Abaye havo yasvei kamei
de'Ravna Nechemya. So רבין Ravin and
אביי Abaye were sitting in front of רבנא נחמיה, Ravna Nechemya, אחוה
דריש גלותא, achuha d'Resh Galuta, the brother of the ריש גלותא, Resh
Galuta, the Jewish secular head of
בבל. Bavel. חזייה דהוה לביש מטכסא. chazaye de'hava lavish metaksa. So here
he was, he was part of like the ruling family, so he
was wearing מטכסא metaksa which is some type of a silk garment,
silk cloak. אמר
ליה רבין לאביי. Amar leh Ravin le'Abaye. So רבין Ravin said to
אביי, Abaye, היינו כלך דתנן. hayinu clach ditnan. Oh that's that כלך
clach that we learned. like he's wearing over there. So אמר ליה,
amrei lei, so he said back to him, אנן שירא פרנידא קרינא
ליה, anan shira parnida karinan lei, we call it שירא פרנידא, shira
parnida, which just as is not just a different name, but no,
no, that's like real silk. That's expensive silk. That's not the משנה.
Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah is talking about the pashmina. Right, exactly. The
משנה Mishnah is talking about discarded, you know, dross silk. That's really
nice silk. That's something else. מתיבי, meitivei, I'll ask you on this,
that
השיראיים והכלך, hashirayim vehaklakh, so silk and כלך, klakh, והסיביקין v'hasivikin and
סיביקין, sivikin, which רש"י Rashi says is also some type of thing
made from silk. How do they translate it?
Corded silk.
Corded silk. Okay.
It's made from the soft part of the silk and some forms
cord.
Okay, there you go. חייבין בציצית, chayavin b'tzitzit, are obligated in ציצית
tzitzit because there's a debate whether things that are not wool or
linen are obligated and maybe they're only obligated rabbinically. So here it
says all these various types of silk are obligated. So the גמרא
Gemara says, תיובתא, tiyuvta, so that's a contradiction. It shows you that
כלך klakh and שיראיים shirayim are not the same. And here אביי
Abaye is so the גמרא Gemara says, no, אי בעית אימא שירא
לחוד ושירא פרנידא לחוד. ee ba'is eima shira lachud v'shira parnida lachud.
No, not necessarily because or it's because it could be that אביי
Abaye said that we call this שירא פרנידא, shira parnida, that is
different than שירא. shira. Now it's not exactly, let me just check
what רש"י Rashi says.
Right, אמר שיראיים לאו היינו כלך. amar shirayim lav hainu klakh. So
it's trying to prove that שיראיים shirayim and כלך klakh are not
the same. Oh because I, I'm sorry, right, I was reading the
גמרא Gemara like תוספות Tosafot that says שירא פרנידא shira parnida is
not is not כלך. klakh. But the way רש"י Rashi seems to
read it is that שירא פרנידא shira parnida is כלך. klakh. And
then it tries to disprove it because it says שיראיים shirayim and
כלך klakh as two separate things. So then it says, no, that's
not necessarily a problem. שיראיים shirayim and כלך klakh could be two
different things, but שירא פרנידא shira parnida could be the same as
כלך. klakh. Okay, so there's a question exactly, are these all are
these different or the same? But again, the upshot is that this
is some type of a silk, most probably some remnant of the
silk process, which is why it was a possibility of using it
for a wick. But you can't. Right. Okay,
ולא בפתילת האידן, v'lo b'petilat ha'idan, and not with the string of
אידן. idan. What's that? אחויינא. achvina. So that's helpful. But if you
remember, it's helpful because a minute ago we did say אחויינא, achvina,
which רש"י Rashi told us was a ערבה, arava, willow. So again,
while the גמרא Gemara before said that that was something that they
were burning as a type of a firewood, but as to use
as a wick, not. Because a wick also remember, not only it
has to be flammable, it has to also draw the oil. Okay,
so this is not going to be good as a wick.
רבין ואביי הוו קאזלי בפיקתא דתמרוריתא. Ravin v'Abaye hava ka'azlei b'pikta d'tamrurita.
They were going in the valley of תמרוריתא Tamrurita wherever that was.
חזינהו להנו ערבתא. chazin'hu l'hanu arvasa. So they saw and some have
with an ע, ayin, ערבתא, arvasa, ערבה. arava. They saw willows. אמר
ליה רבין לאביי, amar lei Ravin l'Abaye, so it seems like רבין
Ravin and אביי Abaye spent a lot of time trying to identify
they were the same people in the earlier discussion what this משנה
Mishnah was talking about. So רבין Ravin said to אביי, Abaye, היינו
אידן דתנן, hainu idan d'tnan, oh this is the אידן idan of
the משנה, Mishnah, this is like the willow. אמר ליה, amar lei,
no, ההיא עץ בעלמא הוא. hahi etz b'alma hu. That's just wood.
So that's wood wouldn't have been used as a wick. קלף, kalaf,
so he peeled the bark back from the tree ואחויי ליה עמרניתא
דביני ביני. v'achvei lei amrnisa d'beini beini. Like we said before about
the willow, he showed him the woolly substance between the bark and
the actual trunk, and that's the issue. So it's not the actual
stick of the ערבה, arava, who would use that as a wick?
But it's this more fibrous and woolly substance in the ערבה arava
tree. And again, that too you would have thought right, that's what
you would have thought use as a wick, but even that is
not reliable enough. Again, it'll either not draw the oil well, it
won't be consistent, it will burn up too easily, and therefore there's
a concern that you will fiddle with the flame.
So the woolly substance of other trees would probably be good then
according to...
Exactly. Anything not listed, right. ולא בפתילת המדבר, v'lo b'petilat hamidbar, the
string of the מדבר, midbar, what does that mean? שברא. shavra. So
רש"י Rashi says it's a type of a grass. I don't know.
How do they translate it?
Nettle, tall grass can be braided and used for wicks.
Okay, some type of a tall grass, maybe that presumably that grows
in the desert. Okay, ולא בירוקה שעל פני המים, v'lo b'yaroka she'al
pnei hamayim, the green the moss on the water. מאי היא, mai
hee, what is this? אילימא אוכניתא דחריצי, ee'leima uchnisa d'charitzai, so if
you're telling me that it is like the moss that grows in
ponds, algae or something, איפוכי מיפרכי, ifuhei mapharchi, then that is brittle.
Nobody would ever be able to try to use that as a
I really can't comment on that, so I don't know, maybe somebody
knows. אלא אמר רב פפא אוכניתא דארבא. ella amar Rav Pappa uchnisa
d'arva. It's the moss that grows on boats.
Okay, so does anybody have any knowledge about any of these realities
about boat moss and pond moss? Okay.
Anyway, but as you've been pointing out, Michael, that first you have
to make it a הוא אמינא. hava amina. Okay, and now that
we've established why it's a possibility, then we're saying but you can't
use. הוסיפו עליהן, hosifu aleihen, and they added to the things you
can't use,
של צמר ושל... shel tzemer v'shel... animal hair. ותנא דידן Utanna didan
and our Tanna why did he not bother mentioning it? Because it
was obvious. צמר מיכזי כביש tzemer michzi kavish if you try to
use wool then it'll just it'll shrivel, it'll burn up, so nobody
would have tried to use it. And שער sa'ar hair, איכרוכי מיכריך
ichruchei michrich will singe and it won't draw flame, so who needed
to add those? Those were self-evident that nobody was going to use
them. Okay and now we switch to the oils. ולא בזפת. velo
bezefet. So the Gemara says זפת zefet is זיפתא. zifta. Okay, there
you go. It's tar or pitch. שעוה shava and what's שעוה? shava?
כירותא kiruta which is wax. תנא tanna עד כאן פסול פתילות, ad
kan psul ptiylot, a Braita says until this part about the זפת
zefet we're talking about wicks that you can't use. מכאן ואילך mikan
ve'eilach once we talk about the pitch and the wax, פסול שמנים
psul shmanim we're talking about things that cannot be used as oils.
So the Gemara says פשיטא, pshita, obviously you can't use these things
as oils. I don't know why it's so obvious, but okay for
them it was obvious. Maybe pitch would be very
smelly, we'll see a discussion about that later, but maybe wouldn't burn
evenly. So the Gemara says שעוה אצטריכא ליה. shava itztricha lei. No,
I needed to tell me about wax. Wax presumably should be a
good type of a thing. מהו דתימא mahu deteima לפסילה נמי לא
חזיא lipsila nami lo chazya maybe you can't use wax for a
wick, קא משמע לן ka mashma lan that wax can be used
for a wick just not for a fuel. For us that's very
hard to understand because our candles both have wax-waxed wicks, which helps
them serve as wicks, helps the flame stay, and the wax is
the fuel. But actually our candles are paraffin, right, they're not wax.
Beeswax I'm assuming is less reliable as a fuel. Does anybody know
about that?
Yeah, beeswax candles supposedly even in some ways better. Like they're smokeless
and all that. But they didn't use candles in the time
of the Mishna and the Gemara. Right, but if they used wax
what would be what would it mean to use wax? Would it
mean to have the wax sitting in a in a kli and
have a wick coming out of it? So wouldn't it effectively be
a candle, a beeswax candle? Yeah. So it's not clear to me
why it can't be used as a fuel.
I guess they didn't use them in that part of the world
at that point because they had they used olive oil.
Maybe it was like melted wax or something and then they were
trying to use it like a type of an oil. It's not
clear to me why wax can't be a fuel. Anyway, it can
be says the Gemara a wick.
And they had different wax than what we have.
Alright right. Well certainly well it was beeswax certainly. קא משמע לן
ka mashma lan that you can use it as a wick just
not as a fuel. אמר רמי בר אבין Amar Rami bar Avin
אטרנא atrna פסולתא דזיפתא, psulta dezifta, this thing called אטרנא atrna is
the dross the remnant of the זפת, zefet, the stuff that comes
out of the tree. Apparently זפת zefet was a pitch that came
from a tree. This comes afterwards. Okay and that's עיטרן itran as
we're going to see. עיטרן itran is a thing we're going to
see. Okay and that's this stuff that comes after the זפת. zefet.
שעוה shava and wax פסולתא דדובשא. psulta deduvsha. Now you know it's
talking about beeswax is the dross of the honey. It's what's so
the Gemara says למאי נפקא מינה lemai nafka mina what does the
Gemara have to tell me what these things are? I mean well
first maybe partly to understand this Mishna but למקח וממכר lemikach umimkar
if you buy it and you say a deal to buy עיטרן
itran you know what you can demand. They're labeling for you. Now
I just want to end by telling you about this issue about
wax because that's relevant for us. If you take a look at
Tosafot עד כאן פסול פתילות ad kan psul ptiylot Tosafot says בנרבונא
biNarvona which is in in Narvona which he's talking he's talking about
contemporaneous to him עושין נר שעוה שלנו osin ner shava shelanu they
do allow wax candles. Okay so מהו דפסולי פתילות נמי לא. mahu
dipsulei ptiylot nami lo.
Anyway so Tosafot then says ולי נראה veli nireh דאם אסור להדליק
בלא שמן de'im assur lehadlik belo shemen כי משביא בשמן נמי אסור.
ki mashvei beshemen nami assur. Anyway
so Tosafot says אלא ודאי לא שנו אלא בשמן ela vadai lo
shanu ela beshemen כי לא הניח בשמן נמי שרי. ki lo hiniach
beshemen nami sharei. So Tosafot basically anyway
there's a question about the Gemara here that says you can't use
wax as a fuel, does that actually mean you can't use their
types of wax candles, which would be a logical type of a
derivation discuss you know a possible assumption. So Tosafot records a debate
about that. We don't have time to get into the arguments back
and forth, but you know obviously for us using wax candles taken
for granted although of course for us I said it's paraffin, but
anyway how exactly you understand what it means not being able to
use wax as a fuel and its contemporaneous application is discussed.